A Guide to the Virginius Dabney Papers 1940-1944
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Virginius Dabney Papers, 1941-1944
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690
This holding consists of 13 boxes of materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This holding was a gift ot the University.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains extensive correspondence, ca. 1930 to 1968, carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal, life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, the African American, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- Materials Relating to World War II
  - National Defense Commission 1940-1941, ca. 30 items (Box 1)
  - Council of Refugee Aid--Roy Veach, Ex. Secretary 1941, ca. 8 items (Box 1)
  - Food for the Small Democracies 1941, 4 items (Box 1)
  - Namesake Towns Committee, Inc.--Mrs. Leonard Hart, Ex. Secretary 1941, 3 items (Box 1)
  - National Committee on the Housing Emergency--Mrs. S.I. Rosenman, Chairman 1941, 5 items (Box 1)
  - National Student Merger Committee--John S. MacCauley, Secretariat 1941, 4 items (Box 1)
  - United Americans--Edward Hart, Ex.Director 1941, 5 items (Box 1)
  - "Young Europe in America," Miss Clara Leiser 1941, 6 items (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Alice Burke, Secretary, Communist Party 1941-1942, 5 items (Box 1)
  - Council for Democracy 1940-1942, 2 folders, ca. 200 items (Box 1)
  - Arthur Glasgow 1941-1942, ca. 75 items (Box 1)
  - Southern Conference for Human Welfare 1940-1942, ca. 20 items (Box 1)
  - United China Relief 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Contractors 1942, ca. 10 items (Box 1)
    Defense eds. 2/28-3/2-3/5, 1942
  - Democracy Programs Executive Committee Office, Civilian Defense 1942, ca. 10 items (Box 1)
  - International Student Service, Mr. Alvin Johnson, Chairman 1942, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Kane, R. Keith, Chief Intelligence Bureau, Office of Information 1942, ca. 35 items (Box 1)
  - The League of Nations 1942, 3 items (Box 2)
  - Dr. Douglas VanderHoof 1942, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Loyal Americans of German Descent, Dr. G.P. Bronisch, Vice President 1941-1943, ca. 30 items (Box 2)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, Director Facts and Figures, Washington, D.C. 1942-1943, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Victory Conference, Louis Bromfield 1942-1943, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Commmittee Canned Fruit, Vegetables, Etc.; L. Metcalf Walling, Adm. 1943, 17 items (Box 2)
  - Davison, Mrs. Henry P. (Food for Freedom, Inc.) 1943, ca. 16 items (Box 2)
  - Ginsberg Case 1943, ca. 5 items (Box 2)
  - The Nation 1940-1943, 13 items (Box 2)
  - Letters regarding removal of Westbrook Pegler's column 1943, 2 folders, ca. 200 items (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Panels Section, Office War Information, Lucian Warner, Chief 1942-1944, ca. 60 items (Box 2)
  - Farm Security Administration 1943-1944, ca. 50 items (Box 2)
  - Freedom House 1941-1944, ca. 35 items (Box 2)
  - Honor Roll 1943-1944, ca. 40 items (Box 2)
  - Red Cross 1942-1944, ca. 40 items (Box 2)
  - Richmond Defense Savings Committee Executive Committee 1941-1944, ca. 100 items (Box 3)
  - Warren, Lindsay C., Comptroller General of the United States 1943-1944, 8 items (Box 3)
  - Editorial "Wanted: A Rededication for America," Correspondence 1943-1944, ca. 25 items (Box 3)
  - Edward R. Stettinius 1940-1944, ca. 100 items (Box 3)
  - Correspondence Regarding Kentucky Education Association Speech April, 1944 (Box 3)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, A.W. Gottschall, Southern Director 1944, 6 items (Box 3)
  - National Committee Against Nazi Persecution and Extermination of the Jews 1944, 16 items (Box 3)
  - Saito, Penny 1944, 6 items (Box 3)
  - Editorial "Roosevelt's Re-election" 10/24/44, 24 items (Box 3)
  - George Creel, "The Plight of the Last Censor" n.d., 1 item (Box 3)
- Materials Relating to the University of Virginia
  - Committee of Academic Standards, University of Virginia, Virginius P. Shackelford, Chr. 1941-1942, ca. 30 items (Box 3)
  - Honor System, University of Virginia 1942, ca. 30 items (Box 3)
  - Institute of Public Affairs 1941-1942, ca. 20 items (Box 3)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review 1941-1943, 13 items (Box 3)
  - Dillard, Irving 1943-1944, ca. 20 items (Box 3)
  - Branch Spalding (of the University of Virginia Alumni Fund) 1941-1944, ca. 100 items (Box 3)
  - University of Virginia--Governor Darden's Program 1944 (Box 3)
- Materials Relating to Richmond Civic Organizations
  - Richmond Council on Adult Education May 6, 1941, 1 item (Box 3)
  - Richmond Chamber of Commerce 1941-1942, 2 items (Box 3)
  - Richmond Tuberculosis Association 1941-1943, 12 items (Box 3)
- Materials Relating to the African American
  - Hampton Institute 1937-1940, ca. 30 items (Box 4)
  - Democracy Defense League for Negro Youth 1941, 3 items (Box 4)
  - Pickens Case February, 1941, ca. 10 items (Box 4)
  - Negroes and Defense 1941, ca. 25 items (Box 4)
  - Odell Waller Case 1942, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
  - Editorial, "The Negroes and the War" 1942-1943, ca. 125 items (Box 4)
  - African Americans, Clippings, Articles 1942-1943, ca. 75 items (Box 4)
  - Lowell, Mass. "Sun." 1940-1941, 5 items (Box 5)
  - J.R. Thomas, Virginia State College, Petersburg 1941, 3 items (Box 5)
  - African Americans, Clipping, Articles 1942-1943, ca. 50 items (Box 5)
  - Negro Memorial Commission, Hon. Wm. A. Wright, Chair 1942-1943, ca. 20 items (Box 5)
  - The Southern Frontier, Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames, M.E. 1941-1943, ca. 35 items (Box 5)
  - African Americans: Atlanta, Durham, Richmond Conference 1943, 2 folders, ca. 200 items (Box 5)
  - African Americans: Atlanta, Durham, Richmond Conference 1943, ca. 50 items (Box 6)
    continuation from Box 5
  - African American Editorial, "The Negroes and the War," letters of rebuttal 1942-1943, ca. 100 items (Box 6)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 1943, 9 items (Box 6)
  - African Americans, Correspondence regarding Atlantic article 1943, ca. 50 items (Box 6)
  - Segregation Correspondence 1943, 2 folders, ca. 150 items (Box 6)
  - Segregation--columns, editorials, Voice of the People, unused letters 1943, ca. 100 items (Box 6)
  - African-Americans FEPC 1943-1944, 6 items (Box 6)
  - Negro Survey Graphic, The Christian Advocate, and ASNE articles, letters 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Segregation 1944, ca. 35 items (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Subjects ca. 1941-1944
  - Miss May C. Fielder, Secretary, Institute of National Policy, William and Mary 1941 (Box 7)
  - Highlander Folk School 1941, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Sweet Briar 1941, 13 items (Box 7)
  - Virginia Long Range Planning Committee, Wortley F. Rudel 1940-1941, 22 items (Box 7)
  - Virginia Policy Committee ca. 1939-1941, ca. 100 items (Box 7)
  - Andrews, T. Coleman 1941-1942, ca. 25 items (Box 7)
  - George Foster Peabody Board 1941-1942, ca. 25 items (Box 7)
  - Harris E. Starr, Dictionary of American Biography 1941-1942, 21 items (Box 7)
  - Virginia Advisory Legislative Council 1941-1942, ca. 100 items (Box 7)
  - Country Club of Virginia 1942, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Francis P. Miller 1941-1942, ca. 50 items (Box 7)
  - Southern Council on International Relations 1942, 6 items (Box 7)
  - Virginia Committee for Constitutional Rights, Aubrey Strauss, Chairman 1942 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Advisory Legislative Council 1941-1942, ca. 100 items (Box 7)
  - Markel, Lester, Sunday Editor, New York Timesca. 1943, ca. 50 items (Box 7)
  - National Civil Service Reform League, Cyrus C. Perry, Field Sec. 1941-1943, ca. 30 (Box 7)
  - Requests for Times-Dispatch1943, 6 items (Box 7)
  - Southern Electoral Reform League, David L. George, Dir. 1941-1943, ca. 35 items (Box 7)
  - Virginia Historical Society ca. 1941-1943, ca. 18 items (Box 7)
  - Saturday Review of Literature, Mr. Norman Cousins 1942-1943, ca. 75 items (Box 8)
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors, N.R. Howard, Sec'y, ca. 50 items (Box 8)
  - Articles requested 1944, ca. 20 items (Box 8)
  - Book reviews 1944, 4 items (Box 8)
  - Bryan, John Stewart 1941-1944, ca. 25 items (Box 8)
  - Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., Hunter D. Farish 1940-1944, ca. 25 items (Box 8)
  - Correspondence concerning N.Y. Times article--July 30, 1944, "The Case for a Non-Solid South" 1944, 15 items (Box 8)
  - Davis, Jackson 1944, 6 items (Box 8)
  - Miss Lucy R. Mason 1941-1944, ca. 40 items (Box 8)
  - New South, Regional Educational Institutions 1943-1944, ca. 30 items (Box 8)
  - Southern Regional Council 1943-1944, ca. 100 items (Box 8)
  - Dabney's Speaking Engagements 1942-1944, 2 folders, ca. 150 items (Box 8)
  - (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence ca. 1941-1944
  - D-H (Box 9)
  - H-M (Box 10)
  - M-R (Box 11)
  - S-V (Box 12)
  - W-Z (Box 13)